Guide to the J.B. Newsom Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
J.B. Newsom papers
1920-1946
SC0490
Newsom, J. B. (John Branner), 1897-
Newsom, John Flesher
1 Linear feet
Papers include "Chinese mining methods in Malaya," 1920, a typescript paper, with some penciled corrections, illustrated with photographs and tables (a later version of this paper was submitted as his thesis for his engineer's degree); reports and related correspondence regarding the Cow Creek deposit, Inyo County, CA, 1925, flotation results on Norwegian ore, 1924, and the Ten Eyck mine, near Somes Bar, CA, 1925; maps by Newsom of various mines near Jamestown, CA, 1925; mining transit notebook on various California locations, 1941-46; and several reprints of articles by Newsom. Also included is a booklet prepared by Newsom for the Stanford tour that was part of the San Francisco meeting of the A.I.M.M.E., 1922. Collection also includes approximately 270 photographs of a family camping trip from California to Canada and Idaho, 1924; the Ten Eyck Mine near Somes Bar, California, 1925; geologic excursion to Death Valley, 1925; tin mining in Malaysia, 1926-27; travel images, 1928; and other subjects.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
John Branner Newsom, son of Stanford professor John F. Newsom, earned his a.b. in geology at Stanford University in 1922 and his engineer's degree in 1924.
Description of the Collection
Papers include "Chinese mining methods in Malaya," 1920, a typescript paper, with some penciled corrections, illustrated with photographs and tables (a later version of this paper was submitted as his thesis for his engineer's degree); reports and related correspondence regarding the Cow Creek deposit, Inyo County, CA, 1925, flotation results on Norwegian ore, 1924, and the Ten Eyck mine, near Somes Bar, CA, 1925; maps by Newsom of various mines near Jamestown, CA, 1925; mining transit notebook on various California locations, 1941-46; and several reprints of articles by Newsom. Also included is a booklet prepared by Newsom for the Stanford tour that was part of the San Francisco meeting of the A.I.M.M.E., 1922. Collection also includes approximately 270 photographs of a family camping trip from California to Canada and Idaho, 1924; the Ten Eyck Mine near Somes Bar, California, 1925; geologic excursion to Death Valley, 1925; tin mining in Malaysia, 1926-27; travel images, 1928; and other subjects.
Access Terms
Newsom, J. B. (John Branner), 1897-; Newsom, J. Branner, Mrs.; Mineral industries--California.; Mineral industries--Malaya.; Photoprints.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - "Chinese Mining Methods in Malaya," Chapters 1-4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Chinese Mining Methods in Malaya," Chapters 5-6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Chinese Mining Methods in Malaya," Chapters 7-9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Method of laying out bore holes (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cow Creek deposit (Inyo County) – correspondence and report, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mining maps – Jamestown, CA, area, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mining transit book, various CA areas, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Pamphlet – Estimate of the Natural Gas Reserves of the State of California, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Report – "Flotation Results on Norwegian Ore", 1924 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Reprints (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - San Francisco meeting, A.I.M.M.E. – Stanford University visit, Sep 28, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "The Ten Eyck Mine, a Preliminary Report," with letter, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - USGS map – Furnace Creek (CA), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Augusta Quarry, Bloomington, Indiana (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Shaft drilling, typescript report and articles by Newsom, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Boring device documentation, 1936-1955 (Box 1, Folder 16)